António Miguel de Jesus Domingues

Schubertstrasse 31, 01307 Dresden, Germany

🛘 (+49) 01575-1976556 | 🔀 amjdomingues@gmail.com | 🏕 http://adomingues.github.io/ | 🖸 adomingues | 🛅 antonio-domingues

Summary_

Bioinformatician with vast experience in the analysis and integration of NGS datasets and a background in experimental biology, which gives me a unique perspective when communicating data analysis and results to collaborators. My research focus has been RNA biogenesis and processing but I am always keen on learning something new. I enjoy experimenting with data visualization to communicate results effectively.

Skills

Core competencies Genomic data analysis, RNA-seq, small RNA-seq, ATAC-seq, Exosome sequencing, NGS

Programming R/Bioconductor, bash, Python, bpipe (workflow manager), git, Cluster computing (LSF / SLURM), Markdown, LaTeX, statistics

Operative systems Linux Ubuntu, MacOS

> Laboratory Cell culture, RNA extraction, DNA cloning, qPCR, animal tissue extraction, single-cell calcium imaging, FACS

Portuguese (Native speaker), English (Fluent), German (Conversational), French

Education

University of Leicester Leicester, United Kingdom

PhD in Cell Physiology and Pharmacology

2006 - 2009

• Thesis title: Cloning and characterization of novel NMDA receptors splice variants in Glia

University of Aveiro Aveiro, Portugal

MSc in Molecular Microbiology

- Thesis title: The role of N-methyl-D-aspartate receptor subunits in Aß induced toxicity
- Host institution: Center for Neuroscience and Cell Biology (CNC), Coimbra, Portugal

University of Aveiro Aveiro, Portugal

BSC IN BIOLOGY 1997 - 2001

- Semester project 1: Phytochelatin synthesis in Pisum sativum L. induced by zinc.
- Semester project 2: Identification of proteins that interact with protein phosphatase type 1 gamma subunit using the yeast two-hybrid approach.

Work Experience __

Scientific Computing Facility (Scionics GmbH), MPI-CBG

Dresden, Germany June 2019 - Present

2002 - 2005

BIOINFORMATICS DATA ANALYST

- · Custom analysis of genomic data.
- Integration of Ribo-Seq and RNA-seq datasets.
- Analysis and pipeline implementation of a long read (PacBio) pipeline to detect genomic insertions.
- · Analysis of mass-spectrometry data.
- Differential gene expression (RNA-seq data).

Institute of Molecular Biology

Mainz, Germany Dec. 2014 - May 2019

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER / BIOINFORMATICIAN

- Developed and implemented pipelines for small RNA analysis (piRNA, miRNA).
- Integrated and analyzed of multiple -omics datasets (smRNA-seq, mRNA-seq, total RNA-seq, ATAC-seq).
- Developed scripts and tools for custom sequencing data analysis.
- Designed and advised on the design of figures and best visualization practices.
- Tested the suitability of new library preparation kits / methods.
- Coordinated the installation of a Zebrafish Facility Management database. I ensured good communication between the IT support, the fish facility manager and the database developer.
- Internal group teaching of UNIX command-line usage and bash.

Biotechnology Center TUD (Biotec)

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER / BIOINFORMATICIAN

Dresden, Germany Oct. 2013 - Nov. 2014

- · Built a pipeline for variant calling from exome sequencing data.
- · Troubleshooting of sequencing issues.
- Advised users on NGS experimental design.
- Liaised with clinical staff and organized the collection and processing of clinical samples.
- Analysis of chromatin associated proteins (DamID-seq and ChIP-seq)
- Differential gene expression (RNA-seq data).
- T-cell receptor profiling.

Max Planck Institute of Molecular Cell Biology and Genetics (MPI-CBG)

Dresden, Germany Oct. 2009 - Aug. 2013

MARIE CURIE POSTDOCTORAL FELLOW

- · Created new stable cell lines with tagged RNA-binding proteins.
- Prepared RNA samples for splice-junction arrays, RNA-seg and ChIP-seg.
- · Analyzed the data of all experiments of my project.
- Collaborated with students and Postdoctoral researchers in conceiving and analyzing experiments.
- Trained doctoral students.

Center for Neuroscience and Cell Biology

Coimbra, Portugal May 2005 - Jan. 2006

CELL CULTURE TECHNICIAN

- Maintained mammalian cell lines and plated them for experiments according the requests of users.
- Ordering and budgeting of cell culture reagents
- · Preparation of cell culture media.
- Teaching aseptic cell culture techniques and best practices to students.

Teaching and mentoring ____

Max Planck Institute of Molecular Cell Biology and Genetics

Dresden, Germany

2011

2011

ALTERNATIVE SPLICING

- Pre-doc practical course.
- · Taught chromatin imunnoprecipitation and 3'RACE.
- · Supervised the students as they carried out the experiments.

Max Planck Institute of Molecular Cell Biology and Genetics

CHROMATIN IP AND RNA LOCALIZATION

Dresden, Germany

- Pre-doc practical course.
- · Taught primer design and qPCR.
- supervised the students whilst they carried out the experiments.

University of Leicester Leicester, United Kingdom

LABORATORY SUPERVISION AND MENTORING OF A MEDICAL BSc STUDENT

2006 - 2007

- Taught molecular biology techniques.
- · Designed experiments and supervised daily work.
- For his project the student received a BSc Honours Degree.

University of Leicester Leicester, United Kingdom

KEY SKILLS IN SCIENTIFIC WRITING AND PRESENTATION (MB1002)

2006 - 2007

- Pre-doc practical course.
- Advising 1st year BSc students on scientific communication.
- Marking essays/presentations.

University of Coimbra Coimbra, Portugal

BASIC RESEARCH SKILLS TO MEDICAL STUDENTS

2003

- · Semester long research project.
- Introduced Medical students to cell biology techniques.
- · Supervised benchwork.

Grants, Honors & Awards _____

INTERNATIONAL

2011 - 2013 Marie Curie Intra-European fellowship for career development, FP7, U.E.

Desdren, Germany Coimbra Portugal

Training program in molecular neuroscience scholarship, Prodep III, U.E.

Advanced courses & workshops.

2018	CSAMA 2018: Statistical Data Analysis for Genome Scale Biology, practical course	Brixen, Italy
2016	Project management workshop, Two day workshop	Mainz, Germany
2013	Programming for Evolutionary Biology, Two weeks, intensive Practical course	Leipzig, Germany
2013	"Software Carpentry", practical course	Freising, Germany
2012	Introduction to Biopython, practical course	Leuven, Belgium
2012	Advanced RNA-Seq and ChiP-Seq Data Analysis, practical course	Hinxton, United
		Kingdom
2012	Principles of Light Microscopy, practical course	Desdren Germany
2012	Pieces & parts: a primer on brain dissection from discrete regions to micronuclei, practical course	Aveiro, Portugal

Publications & presentations

Asterisk (*) denotes equal contribution of the first two authors.

PEER-REVIEWED PAPERS

* Maternal and zygotic gene regulatory effects of endogenous RNAi pathways Almeida, M. V., **A. M. d. J. Domingues**, and R. F. Ketting *PLOS Genetics* 15.2 e1007784. 2019

* RppH can faithfully replace TAP to allow cloning of 5'-triphosphate carrying small RNAs Almeida, M. V., A. M. de Jesus Domingues, H. Lukas, M. Mendez-Lago, and R. F. Ketting Methods X. 2019

PETISCO is a novel protein complex required for 21U RNA biogenesis and embryonic viability

Rodrigues, R. J. C., A. M. d. J. Domingues, S. Hellmann, S. Dietz, B. F. M. d. Albuquerque, C. Renz, H. D. Ulrich, P. Sarkies, F. Butter, and R. F. Ketting

Genes & Development 33.13-14 pp. 857-870. 2019

Tdrd6a Regulates the Aggregation of Buc into Functional Subcellular Compartments that Drive Germ Cell Specification

Roovers, E. F., L. J. T. Kaaij, S. Redl, A. W. Bronkhorst, K. Wiebrands, **A. M.** de **Jesus Domingues**, H.-Y. Huang, C.-T. Han, S. Riemer, R. Dosch, W. Salvenmoser, D. Grün, F. Butter, A. van Oudenaarden, and R. F. Ketting

Developmental Cell 46.3 285-301.e9. 2018

Characterization of genetic loss-of-function of Fus in zebrafish

Lebedeva, S., A. M. de Jesus Domingues, F. Butter, and R. F. Ketting

RNA Biology 14.1 pp. 29-35. 2017

Enhancers reside in a unique epigenetic environment during early zebrafish development

Kaaij, L. J. T., M. Mokry, M. Zhou, M. Musheev, G. Geeven, A. S. J. Melquiond, **A. M.** de **Jesus Domingues**, W. de Laat, C. Niehrs, A. D. Smith, and R. F. Ketting

Genome Biology 17 p. 146. 2016

Abundant cytomegalovirus (CMV) reactive clonotypes in the CD8+ T cell receptor alpha repertoire following allogeneic transplantation Link, C. S., A. Eugster, F. Heidenreich, E. Rücker-Braun, M. Schmiedgen, U. Oelschlägel, D. Kühn, S. Dietz, Y. Fuchs, A. Dahl, A. M. de Jesus Domingues, C. Klesse, M. Schmitz, G. Ehninger, M. Bornhäuser, J. Schetelig, and E. Bonifacio Clinical & Experimental Immunology 184.3 pp. 389–402. 2016

SR proteins are NXF1 adaptors that link alternative RNA processing to mRNA export

Müller-McNicoll, M., V. Botti, A. M. de Jesus Domingues, H. Brandl, O. D. Schwich, M. C. Steiner, T. Curk, I. Poser, K. Zarnack, and K. M. Neugebauer

Genes & Development 30.5 pp. 553-566. 2016

Identification of four functional NR3B isoforms in developing white matter reveals unexpected diversity among glutamate receptors.

Domingues, A. M. d. J., K. M. Neugebauer, and R. Fern

Journal of neurochemistry 117.3 pp. 449–60. 2011

Toxicity of beta-amyloid in HEK293 cells expressing NR1/NR2A or NR1/NR2B N-methyl-D-aspartate receptor subunits.

Domingues, A., S. Almeida, E. F. da Cruz e Silva, C. R. Oliveira, and A. C. Rego

Neurochemistry international 50.6 pp. 872-80. 2007

FK506 prevents mitochondrial-dependent apoptotic cell death induced by 3-nitropropionic acid in rat primary cortical cultures.

Almeida, S., A. M. de Jesus Domingues, L. Rodrigues, C. R. Oliveira, and A. C. Rego

Neurobiology of disease 17.3 pp. 435–44. 2004

PREPRINTS & OTHERS

The IDR-containing protein PID-2 affects Z granules and is required for piRNA-induced silencing in the embryo Placentino, M., **A. M. d. J. Domingues**, J. Schreier, S. Dietz, S. Hellmann, B. d. Albuquerque, F. Butter, and R. F. Ketting *bioRxiv* p. 2020.04.14.040584. 2020

Extensive nuclear gyration and pervasive non-genic transcription during primordial germ cell development in zebrafish Redl, S., **A. M.** de **Jesus Domingues**, S. Möckel, W. Salvenmoser, M. Mendez-Lago, and R. F. Ketting

Identification of Tox chromatin binding properties and downstream targets by DamID-Seq

Jesus Domingues, A. M. de, B. Artegiani, A. Dahl, and F. Calegari

Genomics Data 7 pp. 264-268. 2016

Reviews

* White matter synapses: form, function, and dysfunction.

Alix, J. J. P. and **A. M.** de **Jesus Domingues**

Neurology 76.4 pp. 397-404. 2011

Glia as transmitter sources and sensors in health and disease.

Domingues, A. M. d. J., M. Taylor, and R. Fern

Neurochemistry international 57.4 pp. 359-66. 2010

CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS

Expression of NR1/NR2B N-methyl-D-aspartate receptors enhances heroin toxicity in HEK293 cells. **Domingues, A.,** T. Cunha Oliveira, M. L. N. Laço, T. R. A. Macedo, C. R. Oliveira, and A. C. Rego *Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences* 1074 pp. 458–65. 2006

ORAL PRESENTATIONS

A family portrait: global effects of SR protein depletion on alternative splicing **Jesus Domingues, A. M.** de, M. Müller-McNicoll, M.-L. Ankö, and K. M. Neugebauer 8th Special Interest Group meeting on Alternative Splicing, 2011, Viena, Austria

NMDA Receptor Subunit composition Influences AßToxicity **Domingues, A.,** E. F. da Cruz e Silva, C. R. Oliveira, and A. C. Rego

34th Meeting of the Portuguese Pharmacology Society, 2003, Coimbra, Portugal

SELECTED POSTER PRESENTATIONS

* Activation of the genome in germ cells in relation to transposon silencing and the piRNA pathway **Jesus Domingues**, **A. M.** de, S. Redl, E. Caspani, H. Dill, and R. F. Ketting *Mobile Genetic Elements and Genome Plasticity*, 2018, Santa Fé, NM, USA

Regulation of gene expression by SR proteins: a comprehensive study

Jesus Domingues, A. M. de, M. Müller-McNicoll, and K. M. Neugebauer

Special Interest Group meeting on Integrative RNA Biology (AS-SIG), 2013, Berlin, Germany

Characterization of novel NMDA receptor subtypes

Jesus Domingues, A. M. de, M. G. Salter, and R. Fern

Society for Neuroscience, 2008, Washington, USA

References_

Rene Ketting, PhD Scientific Director, IMB, Mainz (JGU). +49 6131 39 21470 / r.ketting@imb-mainz.de

Karla M. Neugebauer, PhDProfessor of Molecular Biophysics and Biochemistry and of Cell Biology, Yale University. + 1 203 785 3322 /

karla.neugebauer@yale.edu

Andreas Dahl, PhD NGS facility leader, Biotechnology Center of the TU Dresden. + 49 351 458 82351 / andreas.dahl@biotec.tu-dresden.de